<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
    <item>
        <publication-title>Applied Ergonomics</publication-title>
        <title>Variation in work tasks in relation to pinch grip strength among middle-aged female dentists</title>
        <authors>
            <value>Hebo, Ding</value>
            <value>Päivi, Leino-Arjas</value>
            <value>Heikki, Murtomaa</value>
            <value>Esa-Pekka, Takala</value>
            <value>Svetlana, Solovieva</value>
        </authors>
        <highlights>
            <value>The relationship of task variation during dental work history with pinch grip strength among dentists
                was investigated.
            </value>
            <value>The dentists with the most hand-loading tasks were at an increased risk of low pinch grip strength.
            </value>
            <value>It is advisable among dentists to perform as diverse work tasks as possible to reduce the risk of
                decreased pinch grip strength.
            </value>
        </highlights>
        <abstract>
            <value>
                <heading>Objectives</heading>
                <content>We aimed to investigate the relationship of task variation during dental work history with
                    pinch grip strength among dentists.
                </content>
            </value>
            <value>
                <heading>Methods</heading>
                <content>We measured pinch grip strength among 295 female Finnish dentists aged 45–63 years. Variation
                    in dental work tasks during work history was empirically defined by cluster analysis. Three clusters
                    of task variation emerged: low (most work time in restoration treatment/endodontics), moderate
                    (about 50% in the former and 50% in prosthodontics/periodontics/surgery), and high (variable tasks
                    including administrative duties). Hand radiographs were examined for the presence of OA in the wrist
                    and each joint of the 1–3rd fingers. Information on hand-loading leisure-time activities, and joint
                    pain was obtained by questionnaire. Glove size was used as a proxy for hand size. BMI (kg/m2) was
                    based on measured weight and self-reported height.
                </content>
            </value>
            <value>
                <heading>Results</heading>
                <content>Dentists with low variation of work task history had an increased risk of low pinch grip
                    strength in the right hand (OR 2.3, 95% CI 1.2–4.3), but not in the left (1.13, 0.62–2.08), compared
                    to dentists with high task variation, independent of age, hand size, hand-loading leisure-time
                    activities, BMI and symptomatic hand OA.
                </content>
            </value>
            <value>
                <heading>Conclusion</heading>
                <content>The dentists with the most hand-loading tasks were at an increased risk of low pinch grip
                    strength, independent of e.g. symptomatic hand OA. It is advisable among dentists to perform as
                    diverse work tasks as possible to reduce the risk of decreased pinch grip strength.
                </content>
            </value>
        </abstract>
        <keywords>
            <value>Pinch grip strength</value>
            <value>Symptomatic hand OA</value>
            <value>Dentists</value>
        </keywords>
    </item>
</items>