<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
    <item>
        <publication-title>Design Studies</publication-title>
        <title>Visual accessibility in graphic design: A client–designer communication failure</title>
        <authors>
            <value>Katie, Cornish</value>
            <value>Joy, Goodman-Deane</value>
            <value>Kai, Ruggeri</value>
            <value>P. John, Clarkson</value>
        </authors>
        <highlights>
            <value>We conducted a survey of 122 graphic designers and clients.</value>
            <value>We investigated the consideration given to visual accessibility in graphic design.</value>
            <value>Designers and clients do not communicate effectively about visual accessibility.</value>
            <value>We need to develop tools to assist designers with visual accessibility.</value>
            <value>We need to investigate the development of ethical design codes.</value>
        </highlights>
        <abstract>
            <value>
                <heading>None</heading>
                <content>It is essential that graphic design is visually clear and accessible. However, evidence
                    suggests that a lack of consideration is given to visual accessibility in print-based graphic
                    design. Furthermore, effective client–designer communication is a vital component in this. This
                    paper investigates current graphic design practice, with regard to visual accessibility,
                    specifically focussing on client–designer communication. A survey of 122 graphic designers and
                    clients identified that these two groups may not be communicating with each other effectively with
                    regard to visual accessibility, and that there is a need to develop inclusive design tools to assist
                    them with this. This paper adds a novel contribution to our limited understanding of visual
                    accessibility in the UK's graphic design industry.
                </content>
            </value>
        </abstract>
        <keywords>
            <value>graphic design</value>
            <value>communication</value>
            <value>design processes</value>
            <value>user centred design</value>
            <value>visual accessibility</value>
        </keywords>
    </item>
</items>